[Music]
Stanford
University. Let's move on to the draq
equation or let's move back to the durac
equation. I gave you the last time the
simplest example of the durac
equation and
how it's and the durac equation is
always an equation for
firmians. Bzans do not satisfy the durac
equation. They satisfy something else
that we'll come to called the Klein
Gordon equation or Maxwell's equations.
Uh this simple equation now describes
particles which move on a line always to
the right never to the left. And in fact
when pushed we'll discover or we had
discovered that it describes both
particles and antiparticles. We can
think of them as electrons but only
moving to the right. So let me go over
it again briefly. Uh before I do, let's
just write a function on the blackboard.
Good old e to the i kx minus omega
t. If k and omega are
positive, well lord, let's not say
they're positive. Let them be anything
for the
moment.
Uh if you remember the velocity of a
wave, it's strictly speaking the uh the
phase velocity of a wave. The phase
velocity of a wave is just k over
omega. If omega is a linear function of
k, then it's the same as the group. If
if the ratio of k to omega is universal
for all k, then phase and group
velocities are the same. But in any
case, this is the group velocity. Let's
just call it the group.
And when you write this, you may think I
mean the absolute value of K. K can be
positive. K can be negative. Omega can
be positive or omega can be negative.
But I really mean it. K over omega with
its appropriate sign.
If k is positive, if if k sorry if k is
negative and omega is
positive this describes an object whose
velocity is to the left negative. If
both are positive then it's a velocity
moving to the right.
Okay. Again if k and omega have the same
sign it's a wave moving to the right. If
K and omega have the opposite sign, then
this ratio is negative. It's fine. No
problem with it. It just means the wave
moves to the left.
K. Did I write it wrong? Uh, I'm sorry.
It's uh, you're right. It's omega over
K. It wouldn't matter for the sign of
it. The sign is the same whether it's K
over omega or omega over K. Yeah. Okay.
Now let's write down a very very simple
equation
uh for the motion of a particle on a
line. The line is x. Again we have time
and it is d
si by
dx
plus d
si by
dt equals zero.
This describes waves. And in fact, it
describes waves of this form here. Can
you tell whether they're going to the
left or the
right? You think they're going to the
right, huh? Okay. I think you're right.
You are right. Okay. So, let's uh let's
check the s by dx will just pull down a
factor of k. If this were the form of if
this were the form of s, we can use this
equation to tell us what the relation
between k and omega is. The s by dx
taking a derivative with respect to x
pulls down an i
k. Taking a derivative with respect to t
pulls down a minus i
omega. All of that just multiplies what
the original function here. And if we
set it equal to zero, it just says that
I K is equal to I omega or that K is
equal to
omega. And that's obviously a wave that
moves to the right as was
said. Okay. Uh it moves to the right.
But now in general there are two
possibilities for a given well
uh yeah there are two
possibilities we
can plot this relationship here omega
versus k and it's just a straight
line. I've actually left out the speed
of light. Where would the speed of light
go in this equation?
Does it go here or does it go here?
Yeah.
Right. One over C here, right? One over.
Yeah. CT is like X. It'll be one over C
here. So it'll be a C here. Yeah. We'll
set C equal to one for convenience. Then
omega is proportional to K. And you can
see and of course omega if h bar is also
equal to zero is that one uh oh if h bar
is equal to one then omega is also the
energy of an individual
quantum. All right. So over here on this
branch positive K we have positive
energy. Over here on this branch we have
negative energy. Negative energy
electrons. Not a good
thing because any electron which has
positive energy can proceed down this
line here. Boom boom boom boom fall down
the stairs by continuously emitting
photons of positive energy.
uh and uh no electron would be stable.
In fact, the world would not be stable.
It would just want to fill up with more
and more and more negative energy
electrons.
Uh but certainly no electron would be
stable. All right. So what do we do? We
fill up the durac. The durac use the
fact that you can't put two electrons
into the same state. We can stabilize
everything against this boom boom boom
boom falling down the stairs process by
just saying all negative energy electron
states are
filled. They're filled to begin with.
That is the lowest energy state. If you
want to lower the energy the energy of a
system maximally, put as many negative
energy objects into it as you can find.
All right? Just keep piling in negative
energy objects and that will lower the
energy. So filling this up here
completely gives you the direct C and it
gives you the um the ground state which
we'll call the vacuum.
Yeah. Goes just goes. Yeah. If it Yeah.
If the momentum were discreet it would
be like a staircase. If it's continuous
you just slide down continuously
emitting photons as you go. But once you
fill up the direct C, the negative
energy C, then a positive energy
electron has no place to go. Well, it
could fall down a ways, but it can't go
indefinitely. Could fall down perhaps
and emit some
photons.
Uh but it can't go very far. Okay.
So that's incidentally you can see why
it's important that if an equation is
like this that it had better be an
equation for
firmians. Okay. Now we remove a particle
from the negative energy
C. Let's draw let's put over here a
uh here are all the energy levels. Omega
equals zero. Zero energy. Positive
omega. Negative
omega. We fill all of these up. So these
are all filled
up. Can't put any more in there. These
are empty. That's the
vacuum. Now we want to put an electron
in. Well, we can put in a positive
energy electron in. That's fine. We
can't put a negative energy electron in.
But what we can do is move an electron
from the negative energy
C and move it into the positive energies
here. It doesn't have to be
symmetrically located. We can take a
electron from here and put it anywhere
over here. And that creates two objects.
One of them is a hole in the doraci.
A hole in the
duraxi has now the duraci is always
associated with these particles of
negative k and negative
omega. What happens if I remove a
particle of negative k in other words
negative momentum to create a hole? What
does a hole have?
Well, forget charge. Yeah, a positive
charge also. In terms of
momentum, we've removed a particle of
negative
momentum. So, we have created an object
with an extra excess relative to the
vacuum. Relative to the vacuum, it has
one positive unit of momentum. So,
relative to the vacuum, when we remove a
particle from here and put it here, we
create something of positive energy and
positive momentum.
In fact, when we take a particle from
here and here, we create two things. We
create a hole with positive momentum and
positive energy and an electron with
positive uh momentum and positive
energy. So, both the holes and the
particles move to the
right. They both move to the right. They
both have positive momentum and positive
energy. And that's uh okay that's the
fact of this equation here. Positive
charges for the antiparticles, negative
charges. This is just a definition of
course. Negative charges for the
particles, positive charges for the
antiparticles. Everybody has positive
momentum and everybody has positive
energy or all the real objects in the
theory. Okay, that uh that's the simple
dra equation. Sigh is built up out of
creation and annihilation operators in
the standard way.
But yeah, I was kind of confused by this
3D diagram because we're talking about
something
that third line that you kept pointing
to has k and w k and omega both equal to
zero and
here. No, I mean that you have three
axes.
No, this is not three axes.
Sorry, this is just a four. That's just
a 45 degree line. That's omega equals K.
Yeah. Omega equals
K.
Right. Right. No, I think you probably
weren't confused. You were
just confused by the fact that I drew
three axes except that I didn't. Right.
There's two axes and a
curve. Okay. Now, this is a little bit
weird, huh? I mean, particles which can
only go to the right. It's perfectly
consistent, but it has another weirdness
also. The vacuum has an odd property
that it's full of momenta which are
negative momenta. The whole thing must
have an enormous momentum shooting off
to the left. And who cares if that's
what's called a vacuum. Let's just
define it to have zero momentum. But
still, it is a little bit odd. Particles
can only go to the right. Antiparticles
can only go to the right. Nobody goes to
the left. But nevertheless, the vacuum
is filled with these negative momentum
things. It's not very symmetric between
left and right. For one
thing, you may ask, can you what can you
do to straighten it out? In other words,
to make it more symmetric with left and
right. And the answer is you have to
introduce two kinds of electrons. Right
movers and left movers. All right, these
are right movers. So let's indicate it
by putting R here. Right. R for right.
And let's invent another field
describing the left moving particles.
Left moving particles will describe an
equation or be described by an equation
which is
similar
except that we'll want omega to be minus
k. All we have to do is change the sign
of one of these two terms. Doesn't
matter which one. All right. So if we
rewrite an equation let's let let me re
let me write this here as d
site d s right by dt is equal to minus d
s right by
dx that's a right moving wave a left
moving
wave of another field completely
separate field different creation
operators different annihilation
operators describes a different kind of
particle
namely a left
mover is equal to
plus the s right by
dx. If we work out the relation between
omega and k in this case it's omega over
k= minus one. In this case it was omega
over k equals + one h or
left left. These are right movers. These
are left movers. Okay. The only
difference is the sign of this term
here.
Now we have a bunch of left moving
particles with positive energy. In other
words, there's another branch
here. These are right movers. These are
left
movers. Right movers and left
movers. There's another branch with
positive energy, but also another branch
with negative energy.
What do we do to
stabilize the left moving electrons so
that they don't fall
down the stairs? We fill the sea of left
moving electrons. The negative energy se
of left moving
electrons. Now we have as many left
moving as right moving particles in the
sea. And so it's balanced. It's uh it's
symmetric with respect to left and
right.
vacuum or empty space, what we think of
as empty space, no longer has a huge
momentum in one direction. It's been
cancelceled out. And we can now have
left moving or right moving particles or
left moving and right moving holes.
Yeah.
This is the normalization. No. No.
Why do we have
Isn't there some like absolute value?
Why absolute value? Absolute value of
what
uh why why have the whole similar
mathematical operation achieve zero?
Yeah. Yeah. Is there some other way of
achieving the
exclusion without having postulating
filled states? Sure.
Yes. You just call filled states uh you
call filled negative energy states empty
states of holes. You say a filled
negative energy state is an empty
antiparticle state. You just re label,
rename, and now we say this is a theory
of particles and antiparticles, both of
which can move both left and right. And
we never talk about negative energies
again. But
uh I find it well when I first learned
this, I no longer think this way. I
don't think this way anymore. When I
first learned it, I found it rather
comforting to realize that yes, this
whole thing did make sense. And you
could prove to yourself that it makes
sense just by saying um well this is
kind of like a metal where you fill up
all the states and then you make holes
and particles and if a metal is
consistent well this is as consistent as
that. So
um what's the mass of these
particles? They're massless. Why are
they massless? because they move with
the speed of
light. Okay, we'll come back in a moment
and try to make them
massive, right? We'll try to make them
massive in a moment. But just as a
matter of notation, let me teach you a
notation which is important in this
subject. Let's take SI right and S left
and put them together and make a column
vector out of them. Now, this is purely
notation. There's no physics in it, but
it's not a notational trick which we'll
use over and over again. Let's make a
column vector out of them or a column
out of them. All right? And then rewrite
this equation in the following way.
I well
okay dot means time derivative.
Well, let's first of all, let's call
this
S. It's now just S, but it's a column
vector. It's neither left nor right, but
contains both of them. Right? Now, let's
take these two equations and combine
them together into a single equation
for S. All right, for the column vector
S. I'll write down what it is and then
we'll just look at it and see what it
says. What it says is that d by
dt of
s is equal to something that I'm going
to call
alpha times d by
dx. Let's put a minus sign in there. By
definition, as a matter of definition,
what is
alpha? All
right, good
work.
Okay, d by dt is alpha dire by dx. What
is alpha? Alpha is a matrix. Alpha is a
matrix whose value is one for right and
minus one for left. Okay. So what matrix
is it? Alpha is the matrix one minus one
0 0.
In other words, to write it uh to write
it in column vector notation and matrix
notation, it just
says this is equal to alpha, which is 1
- 1 0
0 d si right by
dx d by
dx. Oops, there's a minus sign. There
should be a minus sign in here.
like
that. All right. So, this is just a
fancy trick for writing two separate
linear equations like that and putting
them together into a uh matrix notation
and it's very
convenient but it hasn't done any new
physics. Now, so far the two particles
are both the left movers and the right
movers are massless. They move along the
zax or the x-axis with uh with um the
speed of light. Can we make them
massive? Can we add to these particles
or to these equations something which
makes the particles have mass? So that's
an important thing. After all, electrons
do have mass. They do move with the
speed of light. So for that we have to
remember what the connection between
energy and momentum is for a massive
particle. For a massless particle,
energy is just proportional to momentum.
Omega equals plus or minus K. How about
for a massive particle? So, let me write
over here. Oh, let's yeah. What's the
relationship for a particle of finite
positive, you know, finite mass omega
versus K? Omega
squared equals anybody remember?
Not no that's uh that's
nonreelativistic. We want relativistic
now. Now we're really doing it's obvious
we must be doing relativistic physics
because we're doing something which is
approaching the speed of
light. Right? Non-relativistic is a
special case of relativistic when things
move very slowly. All right. But what's
the formula for a relativistic particle
of
sm? Omega= square of k^2 + m^2.
We need an equation if we want to
describe mass of
electrons where the relation between
frequency and wave number is going to be
this. When m is equal to zero, it just
says omega is k or omega is minus k.
Omega is k or omega is minus k if we
have no mass. That's the case we've
done. Now we want to do the case with a
mass. Okay. How do we do that? not not
obvious. It's not obvious, but uh let's
uh let's play with it a little
bit. Let's rewrite this equation first
in a uh in a neat form which will be
convenient for us. When you take a
wave and you hit it with d by dt, what
it does is it just gives you a minus i
omega. And then we can put s over here
if we like. But let's just remember this
just means d by dt on s gives you a
factor of minus i omega. That according
to this equation is minus
alpha. Now what does this give? d by dx
gives minus i k.
or canceling out the i's and the minus
signs. It says this odd equation that
omega is equal to alpha k. Now this is
just shorthand for this relationship
here.
No, there is not and the reason is
because d by dt gives you minus i or
plus i omega d by dx gives you minus i
k. So that cancels a minus sign. All
right, this is just a
shorthand trick for rewriting this. It
says when you apply these objects to a
plane wave, you'll get uh you'll get the
relationship that omega is either k or
minus k. That's what this alpha is. It's
just an instruction. For the upper
components here, it's one. For the lower
components, it's minus one. All right.
So that's that's a a brief shorthand for
um for these two equations that omega is
equal to k for right movers omega is
equal to minus k for left movers.
Question. Yeah. Do we assume
c= mass particle as far as side
not with mass? This is all we need. If
we ask how fast a particle goes with
this relationship here, what we want to
do is compute the omega decay. That's
the uh that's the group
velocity. Okay? And that's something
like k over square root of k^2 + m^ 2.
And that tells us the velocity of a
particle or a wave uh is proportional to
its momentum divided by k2 + m^2. So
that's built into here how fast the
waves move.
Okay, let's try let's just uh be a
little uh
clever and try to correct this equation.
Omega is equal to alpha
K and let's put
over here. Yeah.
that omega is really a vector
no omega um
omega is really a 2x2 matrix really
strictly speaking it's really a 2x2
matrix and so and uh uh and k is a 2x2
matrix proportional to the uh but
um but as I said what it really stands
for is this it's a trick for rewriting
this in a in an efficient form. I don't
want to have to rewrite these
derivatives every time I work with them.
Just think of omega as I d by dt and k
is minus i d by dx and imagine the whole
thing is operating on a uh on a wave
function. Okay, so this is this is
shorthand. Okay, let's add something to
this now. Something with a mass in
it. I'll write it down. Mass times
something times what? I don't know.
Maybe you're not h beta. Beta. Okay,
let's call it
beta. Don't even know what beta is at
this point. We don't even know what beta
is at this point. Presumably, it's also
a
matrix. Omega equals alpha k plus beta m
plus m beta. And let's require of
whatever alpha and beta are. Let's
require that omega or omega squar is
equal to k^2 + m^2. Let's place that as
a requirement on the matrices alpha and
beta. Oh, I just gave away what beta is.
It's a matrix. Okay. So, let's square
this. Omega squared is equal. All right.
So, let's uh let's let's alpha k plus
beta
m time alpha k plus beta m.
What do we get? We get alpha squar k^
squ. That's good. We want a k squ there.
We want plus beta^ 2 m^
2. That's good. We want an m there. But
now we get some garbage. We get alpha *
beta k *
m. alpha beta k * m and then beta alpha
k * m. k and m are just numbers of
course they're just uh they're just the
momentum and the mass of a particle. So
what do we get? We get alpha beta plus
beta
alpha time
km. This is good. We want that. And it
tells us immediately whatever alpha is
whatever whatever alpha is whatever kind
of mathematical object it is alpha
squared needs to be
one. We also want m^2 there. So beta
squar whatever beta squar is it needs to
be one. But we don't want this term.
This term has no place in this formula.
And so what do we want? We want whatever
alpha and beta are that they have the
algebraic property that alpha beta plus
beta alpha is equal to
zero. This would be impossible with
alpha and betas just being numbers. You
can certainly satisfy this alpha squar
is equal to 1. That's no problem. Beta
squar equal 1 that you can also solve.
But how are you going to solve this
together with this?
If they were just numbers, it would
require either alpha or beta to be zero.
But this says that neither alpha nor
beta are equal to zero. On the other
hand, if they're matrices, it's quite
possible. So let's begin with alpha
squar equals 1. We've already specified
what alpha is. The square of this matrix
is indeed one. The square of this matrix
is just one one.
Whatever beta is, it would also had
better be a matrix
uh whose square is one. But it can't be
the same as alpha. If it was the same as
alpha, then alpha beta plus beta alpha
would just be twice alpha squared and
that would just be two. So it can't be
beta can't be alpha. It also has to have
a square which is equal to one. But
there are more matrices around. Here's
an
example. Beta is equal not beta squared
but
beta. Beta is equal to 0 1 1
0. Let's check that. Let's square it. If
we square it, let's beta squared is
equal to this 0 1 1
0. Okay. In the upper left hand corner,
we have 0 * 0 + 1 * 1. Good. That's
good. And in the
lower, it's it's trivial. You can work
that out yourself. The square of this
matrix is indeed one. That's good. But
more not more important, but equally
important is that alpha beta* beta alpha
is equal to zero. In other words, that
alpha beta is minus beta alpha. Let's
check it. Let's just do these things
once and uh on the blackboard and then
then after that you'll believe
me. Okay. Alpha beta is 1 0 0 minus one.
That's alpha. Beta is 0 1 1
0. This is alpha time beta. Alpha beta.
When I multiply these matrices
row time column I get zero. This one
times this one is
one. This one down here times this is
minus one. This times this is
zero. So that's alpha time beta. How
about beta* alpha? Let's do it in the
opposite order. 0 1 1 0. That's beta.
Alpha is 1 0 0 - 1.
uh the the corner element, the left
corner element, uh left diagonal element
is 0 * 1 + 1 * 0. Good. That's
zero. But let's look at the upper right
hand corner. That's 0 * 0 1 *
-1. So whatever it is, we get a minus
one here, a
zero, a
zero, and a
one. Yeah. A one down here.
So alpha beta is the negative of beta
alpha. This is the negative of this. All
right. So indeed it's true. This matrix
here is square is one and it
anti-commutes with alpha. Alpha beta
plus beta alpha is equal to zero. That's
another way of saying that as matrices
these things
anti-commute. There are other possible
choices. I'll come to another one in a
little while.
Okay, so we've actually found a solution
of this. If we choose for alpha and
beta, the two matrices that are written
here and then rewrite the dra equation.
Let's write it out specifically
uh in terms of its components. Write it
out as real
equations. By real, I don't mean real as
opposed to uh imaginary. I
mean just explicitly very very
explicitly writing down the equations to
see what they mean.
Once we know alpha and
beta can now plug them
in. Okay. So let's uh here we are. What
does it say in in column notation? It
says that sigh
right sigh left
uh let's see here it is omega= alpha k.
So
omega is always the same as i times the
time
derivative. All right. So I * the time
derivative is equal to minus I I
believe times the X derivative of S. Do
I have this right? And the X
derivative of S
left.
Um no I'm missing a minus sign here.
Right. Where did that minus sign come
from? It's alpha. Remember what alpha
is? It's the matrix 1 minus one 0
0. So this minus one here gives you a
negative sign down here. But now let's
write the other term plus
beta time s
itself. Beta time s right s left. What
is beta? Theta is the matrix 0 1 1 0.
What does this matrix do when it acts on
S right and S left? It flips
them. So let's just do it. S left S
right. And now we see what the various
equations are. I s right dot is equal to
minus I
dx s
right plus there's a mass here m plus m
s
left it throws s left into the equation
for s right and likewise i s left dot is
equal to plus i
dx left
plus m s
right that's
explicitly what the equations say can
write them in any number of form I can
also write it as
uh
i dot is equal to i - i alpha d s by
dx plus m beta I in this form I must
remember that these are columns and that
these are matrices. In this form it's
just absolutely explicit
uh what the equations are and beta
interchanges or beta interchanges s left
and s right. So these equations become
coupled equations. The left and the
right movers become
coupled. That's what a mass term does.
Very strange. Nobody would have expected
this before DRA that uh that somehow
what a mass for an electron is is it's a
term in the equation for s right which
is proportional to s left and a term for
s left which is proportional to s right.
Uh yeah imply some conservation momentum
or is it correct? Oh this these
equations are automatically conserved
momentum because they're translation
invariant right but the particle now has
a mass with this equation the electron
now has its mass and its mass is just
m. So that's a remarkably beautiful and
simple equation. It is a beautiful and
simple
equation.
But let's not but it is a beautiful and
simple equation.
Lorenar
is it Lorren invariant? No solution
should not be Loren
invariant. Solutions should be Lorren
covariant. The meaning of that is a
given solution for example might
describe an electron moving with a
certain momentum. If you lurent
transform it, it will be moving with a
different momentum. So it should not be
invariant.
What a Lorent transformation should do
is it should carry a wave function
describing a particle of a given
momentum into the Lorren transform
momentum. And yes, in that sense, this
is uh this is Loren variant. We're not
going to prove it, but it satisfied the
one key test that omega^ 2 is equal to
k^2 + m^2. And that is a lorrenvariant
relation. Omega^2= k² + m^2. And yes
these these equations are lens
invariant. Okay
let's let's go to the limit just to to
look at it a little more clearly. Let's
go to the limit now which we could not
do in this case without the mass term.
Let's go to the limit where the electron
is standing still. You can't make a
massless particle stand still. It always
moves at the speed of light. But once
the particle has a mass, you can you can
study it when it's at rest. At rest
means its momentum is equal to zero.
Okay. Uh to let the momentum be equal to
zero, we can just and where is our
equation? Our equation was
omega was equal to alpha was it minus no
alpha
k plus beta m.
Let's just uh manipulate it at this
level first and then we'll write down
what the equation is, what the uh
equation of motion is. To set K equal to
set the electron to be at rest, that's
the same as setting its momentum to be
equal to
zero. Okay, momentum equal to zero first
of all says that the wave function has
no space variation at all. If k is equal
to zero, there's no space variation.
It's just constant with respect to
space. If the wave function is constant
with respect to space, no momentum, and
we can throw this term
away. In any case, when acting on wave
functions which have zero momentum or
zero uh wave number, then omega is just
equal to beta*
m. So for a particle at rest, its energy
is just equal to beta * m or we can what
does that mean? What does it mean?
Um let's write it in this form
I d by
dt. That's how you get omega by hitting
it with i d by dt. That's equal to beta
m
si. So for a particle at rest where we
can throw away the space variation the
shrouding or the dra equation just
becomes i by dt is equal to beta m * s.
Or to write it another
way, sigh right dot with an i is equal
to
m si left and i s left
dot is equal to
m s
right. Did I get that? No. No. Minus
sign. One of them has a minus sign.
Yeah.
Beta. This one has a minus
sign. No, no minus sign. No, no minus
sign. No minus sign. No minus sign. Beta
has no minus signs in it. Beta is one
one off the
diagonal. So this is the simplified DAK
equation for particles at rest or near
being at rest. Okay, notice that they're
still coupled together in this left
right
way. But to decouple them to find
ordinary equations which are not coupled
in this way all you have to do is add
and subtract these two equations. Let's
add them. What do we get? Then we get
I s let's call it plus s plus means s
right plus s left.
When we add them, I SI right plus S
left is
equal to M times S left plus S right
which is just S
plus. We now have a equation for an
object which is decoupled just one
equation not coupled to anything else.
And what about the other possibility?
Let's subtract them. When we subtract
them, we get
I s minus dot s minus is s right minus s
left. And what do we get on the right
hand
side? Is it ms minus
minus m si minus.
So by adding them and subtracting them
in other words taking linear the
different linear
combinations we find two objects one
which satisfies an equation with a plus
sign and one which satisfies an equation
with a minus
sign which if we just look if we just
imagine that s has a frequency then this
is also the same as omega=
m for the plus sign and
omega= minus - m for the minus
sign. Omega equ= + m for this equation
and omega is equal to minus m for this
equation. So notice what's happening
when the particle is at rest. It also
has positive and negative
frequencies. When it was moving with the
speed of light, sigh left and s right
had positive and negative frequencies.
uh or uh but when the particle is at
rest it's the linear combination s plus
and s minus which have definite
frequencies plus and
minus. So s plus is the field operator
describing positive energy particles at
rest and s minus is the field operator
describing negative energy particles at
rest. What do we do with negative energy
particles at
rest? They're bad things. We don't want
them. What do we do with
them? We just fill the durac sea with
them. We fill them up. So what we have
left over then is the plus electrons
here. The electrons which are linear
combinations linear superpositions of
electrons left moving and right moving
electrons. The linear superposition of
electrons left and right makes an
electron at rest
uh with a frequency or an energy
proportional to mass. The difference
gives you an electron with negative
energy. You just fill up the drai with
it. Okay? So now you have particles with
mass both positive and negative
energies. In fact, for every momentum
there are positive and negative
energies. You fill up all the negative
energies and you leave the positive
energies alone.
There are positive energy electrons and
positive energy
holes. The both holes and particles now
have
mass. Uh the negative energy electrons
when you remove
one has positive energy and so a hole
has positive mass just as an electron
has positive mass or just as the
original particles had positive mass. So
you see that it's it's
um it's a very odd thing as I said
nobody had any idea at all that uh that
the way to make um massive particles in
quantum mechanics was to take left
movers and right movers and have the
left movers coupled to the right movers
in this odd way. Uh it's now a
commonplace uh idea that coupling left
movers to right movers gives you massive
particles but it's still it's a rather
surprising and interesting fact.
Yeah. Is that subus or sub to the right
here? Sinus.
That's
all right. Just in case you don't know
what s plus and s minus are, s plus is
equal to s right plus s left and s minus
is equal to s right minus s
left. What does it mean to add wave
functions or add field operators this
way? You can ask what happens if s right
plus s left acts on the vacuum. What
does it give? Does it give you two
particles one left and one right?
S left plus s right?
Nope. No. They don't need
s left times s right would be two
particles. S left contains creation
operators. S right contains creation
operators. You multiply them together,
it gives
you products which create two particles.
What about s left plus side?
Was it 50/50 chance?
How many particles does it give you?
First of all, one. Is it left moving or
right moving? Combination.
which means
yes which means that it's a particle
with half a unit of probability of being
a left mover and half a unit of
probability of being a right mover. It's
a coherent linear quantum superp
position. So these plus and minus
operators are field operators which
create particles which are linear
coherent superpositions. In other words,
quantum
superpositions of left movers and right
movers, which means they have equal
probability for
either. Okay, equal probability for
either. So a particle at
rest is um a linear coherent
superposition of left mover and right
mover. And a massive particle in general
contains both left moving components and
right moving components. As I emphasize,
it does not mean two particles. It means
one particle with a probability of a
half for in this case for being left
moving or right moving.
And when you look at it and see how fast
it's moving, it's moving. It's at rest.
It's at
rest. It's got zero
momentum. Okay? When I say it's a left
mover or a right mover, I mean to say
that if you didn't have this term in the
equation that it would be moving to the
left or the right, right? Its components
the way it's um it's matrix components
in the original equation describe left
movers and right movers. In the new
equation with the mter term, it
describes something at rest.
Uh yeah, you shouldn't think of it as a
coherent superposition of something
moving to the right and something moving
to the left. They're both at rest or the
whole thing is at rest. But they are
uh okay, here's the way to say it. If
that mass term were not
there and I applied s right plus s left
to the vacuum then it would make a
coherent superposition of a particle
flying off to the left and a particle
flying off to the right. The mass term
modifies the whole thing
significantly and it simply makes a wave
which just sits there. It's neither
going to the left nor to the right. It
just sits there. Uh but it's made up out
of these same
uh objects the upper component and the
lower
component. Okay, so that's how you make
a massive
firmian. All massive firmians in uh in
particle
physics are built out of left movers and
right movers. Yeah. Um are is there like
a one over square root of two over
there? Well, you can put a square. It
doesn't matter because it's a Yeah, you
could uh you can put a square. Sure.
Combination of phase actually matter
exactly what they are or they're just
a number of equations that would be
basically the same.
The phase or the square of two the just
ignoring the square root of two uh that
doesn't change the equation. So we
square it on both sides.
I'm just saying the definition of s plus
and s minus have to have uh basically
same size right and left. Yes. Yes.
You're talking you're asking about the
relative size of the for a particle at
rest. For a particle at rest but they
have a different phase. Could you
different phase means what? We have only
real coefficients there. Could there be
comp? In fact, we do and that's a
consequence of beta having been chosen
to be a real
matrix. All right? There are other
choices of beta that one could have
chosen. The only rule about beta was
that it was an object which
anti-commuted with alpha and whose
square was one. It is not unique. But
once you choose it, you choose it. Once
you choose it, you stick with it. But uh
and they're all equivalent. They're all
equivalent to each other. But
um as a consequence of the particular
choice of beta the coefficient here is
one. Had I chosen other choices, there
might be some phases in there. just I
don't know
question isn't it turned out left right
move a bit misleading because a little
bit I mean if there's a particle really
moving to the right
equation it has both left mo component
and right mo component wave function
right it's it's got things which were
labeled R and L which when the mass term
wasn't there really corresponded to left
moving and right moving waves. Now once
the mass term is there we might we might
give up the uh the um the idea that it's
composed of left moving and right moving
waves that would it is misleading to
think of it as left moving and right
moving waves. It's just a wave that's
not moving at all, but it's built out of
the same mathematical objects which were
left movers and right movers when there
was no mass. Now, that's a mouthful. Uh,
the best thing to do is to play with it
and
perhaps once there's a mass term, give
up R and L meaning right and left and
mean something else by them.
uh
RNL the upper component and the lower
components. Yeah.
So um given in the rest frame um the
firm needs to have uh spin angular
momentum is so far this is a
one-dimensional particle that doesn't
have angular momentum because angular
momentum doesn't make sense in only one
direction in only one dimension. So we
have not gotten to angular momentum yet
which I'm trying but I'm I'm not going
to make it. So so our our wave function
has the firmian creation annihilation
operators. Yes it does. We started the
differential equation we started with
this first order in time in space. Yes.
If we were going after bons what where
did we where did the firmianness creep
in aside from the uh type of the
creation? Okay. Uh that's about it. But
um but the point is with this kind of
equation with specifically this kind of
equation you have no choice but to
quantize it with the rules of firmians
because otherwise you'll have this
terrible problem of an unstable vacuum.
Um we will we have we have not done
relativistic bzons yet and we need to
uh historically of course the dur
equation I think came before the durac
equation but there uh yeah if you uh can
you make it a lent transformation which
removes the
uh the in that upper box there moves
moves the term just to the right of the
equation so that you end up with the one
at the lower box.
Uh in other words, is the lower box
essentially the same as the upper box
but for in a different coordinate
system?
Yeah, a coordinate system which is uh
gotten by inverting the x-axis.
Now I'm talking about the lower box on
this uh on the lower board here. The
box. The box. The box. Ah, here. That
one compared to the one above. Yes. The
box above.
And the upper box above. That one. Those
two boxes. Yeah. I'm wondering if you
can go from the box up the upper box to
the lower box by a Lorren
transformation.
Um.
Oh, you mean I I know what you mean. You
mean supposing we wrote down the
equation for a nonzero momentum, right?
Yes. and solved it. Then could you get
to the equation with zero momentum by
Lorent transformation? Yes. But I would
have to tell you how Lorent
transformations act on
Sai which I haven't done. Right. But not
just wondering
whether in other words this is just as
general in some sense or another as the
as the box above in in if you add Lorent
transformations. That's right. If you
say all right this is the theory of
electrons at rest and now let's lurence
transform them in such a way yes that's
correct but I but you would have to know
how to transform s I understand yeah
that's correct yeah so this that's right
that's that's
another interpretation of mass some
people another interpretation of masses
that it comes from the interaction with
higs bas how does it relate to these
equations
Okay, I will tell
you
the All right. Um,
good. Let me
just be very brief about it at this
point.
How what's the connection between this
formulation of a mass and uh the idea
that Higs fields give particles mass
firmian's mass all right so I'll tell
you um the equations of
motion for the firm
fields and the Higs field the Higs field
is another field let's call it
pi let's call f ofx and it's a scalar
field. It's a scalar field whatever it
is f ofx the equations of motion first
of all contain an equation of motion for
phi let's not worry about what it is but
the durac equation becomes a nonlinear
equation and it becomes a nonlinear
equation in which there's a coupling
constant here and a
phi a coupling constant and a
fi no mass
DAC electron has no mass. And if the
vacuum was such that the field phi were
equal to zero, as you normally would
think in the vacuum, empty space, phi
must be equal to zero,
right? Okay. If that were the case, then
looking at the electron in a vacuum in a
empty space where phi was equal to zero,
this wouldn't be there and you would
just have the massless electron. But if
for some reason, for some reason the
energetics of the Higs field favor the
lowest energy having a nonzero value of
phi. Let's say a constant nonzero value
of phi. f ofx equaling a constant, let's
just call it phi. If that's what the
vacuum, if that's what the um empty
space were like, was filled with phi,
then phi here would just be the constant
value and all of this would play the
role of the mass. So you'd have an
equation. The mass of the electron is
equal to the coupling constant times the
magnitude or times the value of the Higs
field in the vacuum. That's the uh
that's the connection. All right, we
we've said it. That is the connection.
So any place that this can come
from, it'll provide a mass. And in
particular, one place it could come from
is nonlinear equations including
couplings between bzzons and firmians
and for some reason the bzonic field
having a value in the vacuum in empty
space. Yeah. And the one of the things
LHC might give evidence for is the HB.
And can you say more about how it how
they expect that might Well, yeah. Okay.
So we can talk a little more about it
right now. Um I was I was going to go
into the 3 plus one dimensional DAC
equation but since you ask let's uh
let's discuss it a little
bit. The um the Higs field is a bzonic
field and bzonic fields let's call they
have potential energy. They first of all
have energy which depends on the
gradients of the field. Uh both space
gradients and time gradients. Not let's
not worry about that. They also have
energy which just depends on the value
of the field itself. The Maxwell field
uh for example has energy which is e^2 +
b ^2. Electric field squar plus magnetic
field squared. Now both the electric
field and the magnetic field are
proportional to derivatives of uh the
vector potential time derivatives and
space derivatives. So in that case all
of the energy is associated with
gradients of
fields. Uh for the Higs field there are
or for a scalar field you can have an
energy which is a sort of called the
potential energy of the field
vi does not depend on either space
derivatives or time derivatives. It's an
energy density. It's an energy density
in the
field. And in principle, unless you have
some deep principles to guide you, this
V of fi could be
anything, any reasonable function of
phi. Okay. Now, there are some
symmetries for the case of the Higs
field. For example, one symmetry is that
phi a positive and negative phi are
identical to each other. There's a
symmetry of phi becomes minus fi. It's
symmetric. And that means that v of
should be a symmetric function. Why? Why
I say that? It's not important right
now. It's just true. So it means it
should be a symmetric function on the
left and right. If it has a bulge over
here, it should have a bulge over
here. Now for whatever
reason, the reasons are still not
completely settled
completely. VFI is a function which
looks like this.
Why that is so as I said nobody really
knows why it's so but you pick a
function one function is as good as
another it has to be symmetric but
that's all and from what we know about
the laws of particle physics it appears
that the potential energy of the hig
boson looks like this here's here's phi
here's phi equals
z and the minimum of the potential is at
some nonzero values of phi
either over here or over here. You get
to pick one. Is it here or is it here?
Okay. So, if the
potential looked like that, you would
say the minimum was at the origin. If
that were the case, the vacuum value of
phi, the state of lowest energy, the
state of lowest potential energy would
have fi equal to zero and the electron
would have no mass.
Okay,
if for some reasons the field potential
looks like this, then the state of
lowest energy will either be over here
or over here. There will be two
configurations which will otherwise be
identical. One with positive value of
the field, one with negative value of
the
field. Either of them give rise to a
mass
here. either of them give rise to a mass
of v of g * fi and uh you know you can
start asking why did nature choose to
have a field potential which looks like
this not completely clear at the moment
okay
but you see our real vacuum is over
here let's
assume now the
field can be over here in the vacuum but
it can also be pertur urbed. It can
oscillate about
here. Just like a particle and a
potential that can vibrate back and
forth. The Higs field can vibrate. It
can have a
frequency. What corresponds to a
vibrating Higs
field? Right? The frequency of the Higs
field is related to the mass of the Higs
particle. And the excitations of the
Higs field in which it's oscillating are
like any other oscillation come in
quanta. Those quanta are the Higs
particle. So the Higs particles
correspond to oscillations in
here. But if the Higs particle is very
massive, it means it takes a lot of
energy to get this field starting to
vibrate. In the vacuum, it just sits
there. The electron has a mass. Okay? If
it starts to vibrate, that's a Higs
particle. Now, if
the Higs field is coupled in an
interesting dynamical way
to the electron field, then by the laws
of action and reaction, which I'm not
going to be terribly specific about now,
the Higs field will react to collisions
of firmians.
A collision of firmians will start the
Higsfield vibrating. It'll start the
Higsfield vibrating and create Higs
particles, namely these oscillations.
How much energy does it take? It depends
on the mass of the Higs particle. If the
Higs particle is very massive, it means
it takes an enormous amount of energy to
excite one quantum's worth of vibration
in here. So, if a Higs particle is
massive, it means you've got to collide
electrons with a lot of energy to get it
vibrating. Once it's vibrating, those
vibrations are the quanta of the
Higsfield. So the quant the Higsfield is
itself a
legitimate quantum oscillating object
which is described by quanta. Those
quanta are called the Higs
particle and they are coupled to the
electron and other firm fields quark
fields and so forth in such a way that a
collision of two firm fields can start
the Higsfield vibrating. Okay. Action
and reaction. In case if Higsfield
starts vibrating, would it cause the
electron mass to change? Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, if you could get the Higs field.
Now, if you could get the Higs field to
move an appreciable amount, for example,
if you could somehow get the Higs field
to get in balance up here and hold it
there, the electron would have no
mass. All right? Now, this takes huge
amounts of energy. You could uh to
create a region of space and to hold it
there where the Higsfield is up here
would uh require an enormous amount of
energy. so much energy that if you tried
to make that region big enough to do an
experiment in it would you create a
black hole. So it's it's very difficult
to arrange for a region of space to have
a Higs field
uh sufficiently
displaced so that you could see an
appreciable change in the mass of the
electron. But yes, the answer is yes.
Electron, a quark or anything else, the
answer is yes. that uh that a
displacement of the Higs field would
correspond to a effectively a shift in
the mass of the electron.
So what what is the uh
reason we think there is a H field and
electron has a mass h no we don't think
there's only one necessarily so each
particle well electrons and quarks each
have their own to generate their energy
are there
no
um in the in the standard model of
particle physics is one higs and it does
the work for all of the particles,
electrons, uh quarks and so forth. In a
super symmetric version of it, there are
two. One of them for uh for up well
there's two but no more than two. And uh
it's not that one is for electrons and
one is for
quarks. It's a little more complicated
than that. uh in some ways more
complicated and in some ways
simpler. So uh in a super symmetric
theory there are two Higs bosons. In a
regular ordinary theory there's only
one. And the Higs field is a little more
complicated than this. I didn't give it
its full glory but I gave you the basic
idea that uh uh that the Higs particle
is an oscillation at the bottom of this
potential well. The shift of the Higs
field in the vacuum is the origin of the
mass of the electron and and the quarks.
And the real question is why do you have
to go to such lengths? Why don't you
just give the electron in the equations
a mass in the hell with the Higs field
and that has a lot to do with the weak
interactions and
uh and unification in the super
symmetric case. Then are the two Higs
particles antiarticles? No, no, no, no,
not really. Um, it just is one which
gives mass to up quarks and the other
one which gives mass to down quarks and
electrons. Uh, and it's a little funny.
I mean, it's a technical feature of
super symmetric theories which in itself
is not terribly interesting. You
uh not not terribly conceptually
interesting. It's just to keep all the
symmetries and everything you're forced
to throw in two Higs boson. It's one of
the to my mind one of the ugly features
of super symmetric theories but it may
be true ugly or not.
So question if the Higs particle has
mass where does that mass come from?
from the
Hicks. No, no.
Uh, yeah, we're getting in over our
heads now because much of this No, no, I
mean, we want to we want to take it
easy. Where does the Higs mass come
from? Nobody knows at the moment.
Uh, the real question is not why the
Higs particle has a mass. The real
question honestly is why the Higs
particle mass is so
small. Um okay there
um there are symmetries involved in this
whole story. Symmetries are very
important to the story. Let's suppose we
had a
uh um a reason to believe that uh that
there was a
symmetry. Um let's see what uh what is
the
symmetry let's come back to it let's
come back to it this is an interesting
model to explain to understand the
relation between symmetries and particle
masses let's come back to it but I will
tell you that the basic symmetry I'm
thinking about is this left right
symmetric uh symmetry here if the vacuum
was left right symmetric it would mean
left right now doesn't mean uh in space
it means in field space here then it
would mean the vacuum value of the field
would have to be zero and the mass of
the electron would have to be
zero. So it's the breaking of symmetry
which is what provides the mass of the
electron. Now many of the particles the
basic structure of the theory is such
that there are symmetries which would
tell you that if the vacuum was
symmetric those particles would have to
be
massless and they only can get a mass by
virtue of the vacuum being asymmetric
like that. That is all of the particles
that we know.
All of the particles that we know of
with the exception of one, namely the
photon, get their mass or would be
massless, would not have mass if the
Higs field was at the center here. The
photon is an exception only because it
doesn't have any mass. It's not an
exception. It has no mass. Uh but all
the particles that have mass have mass
because the Higs field is not at the
center.
Um that's where the oh I'm sorry there
is one
exception apart from the photon the Higs
particle itself the Higs particle itself
could have a mass even if it didn't have
an offset like this so the Higs particle
gets its mass from a totally different
mechanism than electrons quarks z bzons
w bzons all those other particles have
mass because of a mechanism like this
only the hig boszon gets its mass from
some other mechanism but we don't we
haven't gotten far enough yet to uh to
discuss that we'll come to it how about
a graviton h how about a gravitton does
that have a mass no it has no mass
within the higs particle higs field
it has no mass graviton yeah okay so
it's like a photon like a photon the
photon is not unique it's not what would
not the photon is not unique
a zero mass, right? The graviton is the
only other in theory. In theory, well,
we don't know that it's the only other
one. It's the only of the of the
known of the known objects in nature.
The only things which move with the
speed of light are photons and gravitons
of the known things. At one time it was
thought that nutrinos were massless but
we now know that nutrinos have a tiny
little bit of mass which means that
there's this left right coupling between
them. Uh it's very small. Now why it's
so small is another question and we'll
try to get to these things but
uh should we talk about the four dimens
the three plus one dimensional dra
equation? Yeah, the pattern the pattern
is once once you understand
this the pattern is very
similar. Again particles are described
or fields waves are described by a
frequency and a wave vector. The wave
number becomes a wave vector which is
proportional to the momentum of a
particle. The wave vector has components
kx, ky and
kz. And durac began by writing down a
generalization. Actually you I can write
the same equation omega equals remember
what it was alpha*
k. Was there a minus? I think I had a
minus in there. minus alpha *
k and dra said let's generalize this oh
plus beta m plus beta
m again standing for a particular
equation a particular differential
equation time derivatives space
derivatives and just mass
did I leave out the minus let's see
where
Uh,
I'm not sure. I've lost track of whether
there should be a minus there or not.
Maybe not. No, no minus. Take it back.
No minus. I take it
back. No minus at
all. Okay. Omega= alpha k plus beta m.
Now their act said look let's try this
in three-dimensional space I have three
components of momentum I'll call this
momentum now and therefore I have to
have three components of alpha it had
better be of the form let's call it
alpha 1 k1 plus alpha 2 k2 plus alpha 3
k3 components of k k 1 2 and three now
mean x y and
z alpha alpha 1 k1 plus alpha 2 k2 plus
alpha 3 k3 is the natural generalization
of this plus beta m he started out with
this he said that's the most general
linear thing I can write down
uh it's nice and simple let's see if we
can do business with an equation like
this with alpha and betas being
matrices in such a way that omega^ 2 is
equal to k^2 + m^2 we will require
higher omega^ 2 = kx^2 or k1 2 + k2 2 +
k3 2 + m^2. That's relativity. All
right. Now, of course, there's more to
relativity than just this equation, but
he started with that. He said, let's try
that. Let's see if we can do business
with that.
Hm.
Good. Somebody's saying something, but I
can't hear what it is. Okay. All right.
So, let's just square it. Omega squared.
What are we going to get? Let's just
multiply. Alpha 1 k1 plus alpha 2
k2 plus alpha 3 k3 plus beta
m. you know why he chose this particular
form is a historical fact. It was
simple. It was nice and simple.
Uh and uh let's try it. It was in that
spirit. Let's try it and see what we
get. All right. So, first of all, we're
going to get things like alpha 1^ 2 k1
2. We're going to have similar things
for alpha 2^ squar k2 alpha 3 squar plus
k3 squared. It's pretty obvious we had
better choose all of the the square of
each alpha to be equal to one. Okay. So
we can write that then alpha subi squar
equals one for one for alpha for i
equals 1 2 and 3. The square of each
alpha matrix each one of them has to be
one. That's the first
condition. Let's let me write it up
here. alpha 1^2 = alpha 2^2 = alpha 3^2
= 1 all three of them. Now what about
beta? When we multiply beta squar we're
also going to want to match
uh where is the uh yeah we're going to
want to match this. So also beta squar
would better be equal to one.
We're going to get some other terms.
We're going to get terms for example
which have K1*
K2. They'll come from two places. We'll
have K1 K2 from these two terms. Can
everybody see it? Okay. But we'll also
get terms from these two terms. Same
term K1 K2. So what do we have for K1
K2? We'll have K1 K2. We'll have alpha 1
alpha
2 plus alpha 2 alpha 1. What do we want
to do with that? Zero. Got to be zero.
And more
generally, the anti-commutator of two
alphas had better be zero if they're not
the same. If they're not if they don't
have the same
index. Okay. So we have alpha i alpha j
plus alpha j alpha i equals zero i not
equal to
j. For i equal to j it has to be one. So
you could write this in the form if you
like notation alpha i alpha j plus alpha
j alpha i equals delta
j. Another way of saying zero when I not
equal to J, one when I equals to J. What
about the terms which have products? For
example, K * M. We're going to have K *
M K1 * M. K1 * M from here and K1 duck
out of the way. K1* M from here and K1*
M from
here. All right. So we'll also have to
have each one of the
alphas plus dot dot dot dot dot dot dot
plus
k1
m alpha 1 beta plus beta alpha
1. We have to have the alphas all
anti-commute with
beta. Okay. So we have to have for every
alpha alpha i beta plus beta alpha i
must equal
zero. If we can satisfy these
relations four matrices al
together three alphas and one beta very
symmetric every one of them
anti-commutes with any other one of all
four of them this is symmetric.
uh if the four matrices first of all
they all have to square to one they all
have to anti-commute with each other and
that's it basically if we can find four
such
matrices then we can find a wave
equation of the same column matrix type
which will give us in four dimensions 3
+ 1 dimensions will give us omega^2= k^2
+ m^2 so dra said himself self the task
of finding a collection of four matrices
which satisfy this rule. His first
observation must have been a little bit
of a disappointment is that you can't do
it with 2x two
matrices. You can find three matrices of
the right form which are square to one
and which mutually
uh anti-commute in this way. you can
find three of them, the three poly
matrices, but there is no fourth
one. Uh, and so first attempt failure. I
don't know if it was Dak's first
attempt. He probably knew this so
intuitively that I didn't even bother.
But, uh, all right. The first case where
you can have matrices which satisfy this
is in four, not four dimensions of
spacetime. That's not the point. 4x4
matrices. 4x4 matrices. There are 4x4
matrices which satisfy all of these
conditions. There are no 3x3 and no 2x2
matrices. Just first case is 4x4
matrices. So durac figured out the 4x4
matrices which uh which satisfied these
rules. I'm going to give them to you.
I'm going to tell you what they are. You
can uh study them
yourself. I'm not going to uh do the
details.
4x4 matrices which satisfy these rules.
They are called of course the durac
matrices. Incidentally that raises a
puzzle from the beginning. Um the 2x two
matrices corresponded had something to
do with moving left and moving right.
Okay. What are these 4x4 matrices? what
are the four possibilities associated
with the four
matrices? Uh, and that's something we'll
come to, I think, next time. I don't
think we'll do that tonight, but the new
ingredient is
spin. That
[Music]
uh Okay. And we're going to have to
learn a little bit about angular
momentum before we can learn about spin.
Okay. Okay, so let me tell you what the
minimal set of matrices, they're not
unique. They're not unique up to some
simple
transformations, but they're
equivalent. Uh not unique, but
equivalent in the same sense that I can
pick if I'm interested in mutually
orthogonal axes in space, mutually
orthogonal axes are not unique. There's
another set of mutually orthogonal axes.
They're not unique but they are
equivalent in that the laws of physics
in in either set of axes are the same
and you can make transformations from
one to the other. In the same sense the
choice of direct matrices is not unique
but equivalent. And here's a
particular
solution. Okay. So
beta is equal to 1 0 0
0 1 0 0
0 - one 0 0 0 -
one. Okay, that's beta. Now before I
write the others, I want to simplify.
Well, maybe
[Music]
yeah, I think I'll write them without
simplifying the notation. Okay, that's
beta alpha
1. And of course, it's your job to go
home and check these algebraic
relations.
Okay. 0 0
[Music]
Uh 0 1 1
0 0 1 1
0 0
0 alpha
equals 0 0 0.
Now I could start saving myself work
by just dividing these things into 2x
two structures and call each one of
these give each one of these 2x2
matrices a name. But I'll do that next
time. Uh here goes alpha 2. Anybody know
what comes
next? Minus I I
Z. And down here we
have 0 minus I I
Z and then 0 0
0 alpha
3. Surely you can
guess. Somebody want to take a stab at
it.
No. 0 0 1
1 -
one 0 0.
No. One
0 - one 0 0
0. A
more nifty notation is to divide things
into blocks of 2x two
matrices. All right. Each one a block of
2x2
matrices and then write them in the form
beta is equal to the unit of call
I for identity or unit matrix here unit
2x2
matrix 0 for 0
0 minus
I where each entry is now a 2x2 matrix.
Okay. And
alpha is equal to 0 sigma
sigma
0 where these matrices are the three pi
matrices. The three poly matrices. If
you don't know what they are, here they
are. Sigma
1, sigma 2, and sigma 3. We're going to
come back to these matrices. They're
very
important. Okay, these
objects satisfy the DRA anti-commutation
relations. And if you write a wave
equation, what would the wave equation
be? The wave equation would be
um well, let's write it
down. You first of
all make a four component S. S 1, S 2,
S3, S4 corresponding to the 4x4 matrix
entries. And you write that derivative
of
S with respect to T
*
I is equal to
minus
alpha
I with an I derivative of S with respect
to X I.
X I means X Y and Z. This means alpha 1
times derivative with respect to X alpha
2 derivative with respect to Y and so
forth summed over I and then
plus beta M s. That's the famous DAC
equation and it stands for four
equations. four equations in which the
components get a good deal more mixed up
than in the one in the in the easier
case the one dimension they get more
mixed up because there's a lot of off
diagonal uh matrix elements here that
means when they're off diagonal it means
the matrix elements get mix up the uh
the different uh components in a fairly
intricate way but still it's a coupled
set of linear differential equations for
four components
where the matrices sort of entangle or
entangle is a technical term I shouldn't
use it where the um where the matrices
couple the various components together
it's called a direct equation
um we will come back to it and the next
time we'll discuss where spin comes from
where spin comes from is
the extra doubling if you like of the
size of the matrices.
Is there a C that sort of Oh, sure.
function as the M over here.
Sure. What? Well, you have an M over
here. And you want to know where the C's
go?
Um, actually, I'm trying to think of it
as a kind of a four vector type of a
thing. It's not a They're not four
vectors. The spinners, they're not four
vectors.
They're four component objects, but
they're not four vectors. The four here
is not the same as saying that space has
four
dimensions. Uh it happened in the
previous case that spacetime had two
dimensions and the matrices were 2x
two.
However, that uh was just an accident.
And in this case, it's also an accident.
As you go between different dimensions,
the matrices get big fast and they're
not they're not the same dimensionality
as a
space. They're always even dimensional
and they're always of dimension 2 to the
n in any
dimension. In any dimension of space,
the size of the matrices is always two
to some power. So the basic structure is
we have some mi on on one term and and
some sort of momentum on the other term.
some sort of momentum where that's right
where some sort of momentum on the other
term but where the matrices mix up the
components in some slightly intricate
way. It's again interesting to study the
case with no momentum of a particle at
rest and then it just has this. And if
you notice beta has two positive entries
and two negative entries. It means that
there are positive energy states and
negative energy states. Same
deal. Same deal. Fill up the negative
energies.
Shouldn't that alpha equation uh be
alpha i and z sigma i sigma i z upper
right?
There's also a two in the uh left hand
left top board left top board right
left top board right before the delta
here two oh is there a two
right you are right there is a two here
thank you why is there a two there let's
see alpha 1^ 2 should be one but this is
obviously if both i and Say a one. This
is alpha 1^ 2 plus alpha 1^ 2 which is
two. That's right. There is a
two is
having a matrices. Is that a case of
like getting ahead of
boy was it absolutely yes sir. I mean
until Dak wrote down this equation
antiparticles had never been heard of.
Spin had be been heard of but nobody
knew where it came
from. What uh
Dak he postulated this equation and then
tracked down its consequences and one of
the consequences was antiparticles. The
other consequence was spin. Like it or
not spin was there. So uh yes that's
right.
Was it a similar story to what you
mentioned earlier about the theorem of
relativity and quantum mechanics giving
us firmians and bzons? Which came first
the theorem or the the empirical
evidence? Oh, the empirical evidence. Oh
yes. No. uh the
theorem the theorem was much later and
it keeps getting the the uh as with all
theorems there are assumptions that you
begin with and sometimes in the
beginning the assumptions were let's
just take free fields which meant fields
which didn't interact with other fields
completely linear equations and see
what's possible
uh it was proved in that case and then
people studied coupled fields builds and
uh and got more and more elaborate the
theorem.
[Music]
Um by now I don't think anybody doubts
that the only possibilities of Bzons
incidentally this is a statement about
threedimensional space one dimension of
time relativity in three dimensions of
space one dimension of time in two
dimensions of space and one dimension of
time it's different there are things
which can interpolate between um bzons
and firmians
uh and they're interesting ing but uh in
four dimensions that's it bzzones and
firmians and that's all in higher
dimensions
also for the subscript of s for the four
components of sigh is there a customary
index
well sure you uh what should we call the
index we'll need a label what do you
call oh you can name it I mean uh I
don't want to use I because we've used i
at least twice in this
equation at least twice in this
equation. We can we can fix that square
root of minus
one. Right? Um now there's I but I would
not want this I labels what what is this
I space one X Y and Z but now there's
also a label here. So what shall I call
it? Alpha. Let's call it oh boy we've
already used alpha.
M and then
we already used M. So okay, there isn't
a customary one. How about J something
in Arabic case? P and Q. P and Q. Okay,
so this is P. The matrices themselves
have two
indices P Q and this would be
Q. And this would also be PQ and this
would be Q. And in this case, P and Q
would run from one to four.
You don't really need those in because
you can just use matrix multiplication.
What's that? Just use matrix
multiplication. That's correct. Sure.
Yeah. Yeah. You know, but if you wanted
to know where all the hidden indices are
and things and there's there's a
symmetric way to write this equation so
that it looks more relativistic. And
maybe I'll write it down next time.
Uh basically, yeah, there's a more
symmetric way to write it, but
um this does the trick. In any case,
that's the DRA equation or its simplest
uh
incarnation. And
um next
time, what did I say we would do next
time?
Spin. Spin. Spin. and the wave fields
for relativistic
Bzans. Doing that we will be ready to
start to talk about real particle
physics. We need to talk about what the
theory of Bzans is like. You know about
half the particles in nature are
bzons and durac equation is not the
right description for them. We need to
talk about that a little bit. And then
we move on
to quarks,
lepttons, zbzons, x bzons, no x bosons,
y bzons, hig bzons, photons, and uh and
try to make a little bit of order out of
the
mess.
[Music]
Um, good. Okay.
Symmetries. We have to talk about
symmetries. More about symmetries.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.